<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The wise taken in their craftiness, and their wisdom made manifest to be foolishness with God; and their actions discovered to be contrary to the pure law of righteousness given forth by the pure law-giver, Christ Jesus the light; by which light some one judge, or judges of this nation are made manifest, how he, or they have acted contrary to the law of God, and the law of this nation; and contrary to all the kings, rulers, and judges, spoken of in Scripture; by setting fines upon men, and sending them to prison till payment of the same, for not putting off their hats, and stand bare-headed before them in their court of assises, and goal-delivery. Also, here is shewed, that it is no sin for a man to stand with his hat on his head, before any emperor, king, ruler, judge, justice, or other magistrate, either alone, or in open court; neither is the putting the hat off, and standing, bare-headed before them, the honour that is due unto magistrates, which the Scripture speaks of. / VVritten by, me who am known by the name of Henry Clark.</title>
            <author>Clark, Henry, 17th cent.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1656</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 59 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A79865</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C4459</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E882_3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R207280</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99866341</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99866341</idno>
            <idno type="VID">168389</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A79865)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 168389)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 133:E882[3])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The wise taken in their craftiness, and their wisdom made manifest to be foolishness with God; and their actions discovered to be contrary to the pure law of righteousness given forth by the pure law-giver, Christ Jesus the light; by which light some one judge, or judges of this nation are made manifest, how he, or they have acted contrary to the law of God, and the law of this nation; and contrary to all the kings, rulers, and judges, spoken of in Scripture; by setting fines upon men, and sending them to prison till payment of the same, for not putting off their hats, and stand bare-headed before them in their court of assises, and goal-delivery. Also, here is shewed, that it is no sin for a man to stand with his hat on his head, before any emperor, king, ruler, judge, justice, or other magistrate, either alone, or in open court; neither is the putting the hat off, and standing, bare-headed before them, the honour that is due unto magistrates, which the Scripture speaks of. / VVritten by, me who am known by the name of Henry Clark.</title>
                  <author>Clark, Henry, 17th cent.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 12 [i.e. 18]] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Giles Calvert, at the Black spread-Eagle, neer the west end of Pauls,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1656.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Pages 16-18 and misnumbered 9, 8, 12.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "June. 15".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Lese majesty --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Civil rights --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:168389:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE WISE TAKEN IN THEIR CRAFTINESS, AND Their Wiſdom made manifeſt to be Fooliſhneſs with God; and their actions diſcover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be contrary to the pure Law of Righteouſne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s given forth by the pure Law-giver, Chriſt Jeſus the Light; by which Light ſome one Judge, or Judges of this Nation are made manifeſt, how he, or they have acted contrary to the Law of God, and the Law of this Nation; and contrary to all the Kings, Rulers, and Judges, ſpoken of in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; by ſetting Fines upon men, and ſending them to Priſon till pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the ſame, for not putting off their Hats, and ſtand bare-hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded before them in their Court of Aſſiſes, and Goal-Delivery.</p>
            <p>ALSO, Here is ſhewed, that it is no ſin for a man to ſtand with his Hat on his head, before any Emperor, King, Ruler, Judge, Juſtice, or other Magiſtrate, either alone, or in open Court; neither is the putting the hat off, and ſtanding, bare-headed before them, the honour that is due unto Magiſtrates, which the Scripture ſpeaks of.</p>
            <q>
               <p>And ſhall not Ged avenge his own Elect, which cry day and night <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s him, though he bear long with them: I tell you that he will avenge th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m ſpeedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; he that ſhall come, wil c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>me, and wil not tarry: <bibl>
                     <hi>Luke 18.7.8. Heb. 10 37.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
               <p>He leadeth the Counſellors away ſpoyled, and maketh the Iudges fool<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>: He loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the bonds of Kings, and girdeth their loyn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> with a g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e. He leadeth Princes away ſpoyled, and overthroweth them mighty. There is a ſp <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>an, and the inſpiration of the Almighty giveth them underſtanding. Great me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> are not alwayes wiſe, neither do the aged unde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtand judgement, <bibl>
                     <hi>Job 12.17, 18, 19. Job 31.8.9.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>VVritten by, me who am known by the Name of</hi> Henry Clark.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Giles Calvert,</hi> at the <hi>Black-ſpread-Eagle,</hi> neer the Weſt end of <hi>Pauls,</hi> 1656.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:168389:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:168389:2"/>
            <argument>
               <p>Here is the wiſe taken in their craftineſs, and their wiſdome made manifeſt to be fooliſhneſs with God; and their actions diſcovered to be contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the pure Law of Righteouſneſs, given forth by the pure Law-giver <hi>Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> the Light; by which light ſome one Judge, or Judges of this Nation are made manifeſt, how he or they have acted contrary to the Law of God, and the Law of this Nation; and contrary to all the Kings, Rulers, and Judges ſpoken of in Scripture, by ſetting fines upon men, and ſending them to pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon till payment of the ſame, for not putting off their hats, and ſtand bare-headed before them in their Court of Aſſizes, and Goal-Delivery, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </argument>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>OD in the beginning created man in his own image,<note place="margin">Gen. 1.26, 27.</note> and after his own like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, in holineſs and righteouſneſs, which is after the image of God, created he man, holy and upright: For ſaid <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi> God created man upright:<note place="margin">Ecleſ. 7.29.</note> But they have ſought out many inventions; man turning from the light, and going out from the preſence of God, who is light, runs into the tranſgreſſion, and then ſought out the invention how to hide themſelvs from the preſence of the living God, who is Light, and makes manifeſt all darkneſs, and evill deeds whatſoever that are reproved. <hi>Adam</hi> after his fall into the tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:168389:3"/> he ſought out in his invention, how to hide and cover himſelf, <hi>Eve</hi> being deceived by the Serpent was in the tranſgreſſion, ſhe took of the fruit of the tree of knowledge of good and evil, which God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded the man, ſaying, <hi>Thou ſhalt not eat of it; for in the day that thou eateſt thereof thou ſhalt ſurely die;</hi> and ſhe did eat, and ſhe gave alſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to her husband with her, and he did eat alſo; and their eyes being o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened, they knew that they were naked; then they ſought our an inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ion,<note place="margin">Iſa. 30. i.</note> and ſewed fig-leaves together and made themſelves aprons, to cover themſelves therewith; but the wo was, and is unto them that be covered, but not with the Spirit of the Lord. The fig-leaves being too ſhort a covering for them, (they ſought out another invention) they went and hid themſelves in the Garden among the trees, from the preſence of the Lord; but the Lord God walking in the Garden in the cool of the day,<note place="margin">Read the ſecond &amp; third ch. of <hi>Gen.</hi>
               </note> called unto <hi>Adam,</hi> and ſaid, Where art thou? and <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> ſaid unto the Lord God, I heard thy voice in the Garden, and I was afraid becauſe I was naked, and hid my ſelf. Here you may ſee how the wiſe was taken in his craftineſs, and his invention ſtood him in no ſtead, neither ſaved him from the preſence of the Almighty, nor hid him from the judgement of God: for God ſaid unto <hi>Adam,</hi> Becauſe thou haſt hearkened to the voice of thy Wife, and haſt eaten of the Tree of which I commanded thee, ſaying, Thou ſhalt not eat of it: Curſed (ſaid the Lord) is the ground for thy ſake, in ſorrow ſhalt thou eat of it all the dayes of thy life; Thorns and Thiſtles ſhall it bring forth unto thee; in the ſweat of thy face ſhalt thou eat bread, till thou return unto thee ground, for out of it waſt thou taken; for duſt thou art, and unto duſt ſhalt thou return.</p>
            <p>So likewiſe after the Flood, the whole earth being of one Language and of one ſpeech, the people as they journeyed from the Eaſt, they found a Plain in the Land of <hi>Shinar,</hi> and they dwelt there, (and being there at eaſe, they ſought out an invention) they ſaid one to another, Go to, let us make Brick, and burn them thorowly: and they had Brick for Stone, and they had Slime for Motter: and ſaid, Go to, and let us build us a City and a Tower, whoſe top may reach up unto Heaven, and let us make us a Name, leſt we be ſcattered abroad upon the face of the whole earth. See here, how men in the pride of their hearts, and in their inventions, how they ſought for their honour: Let us make us a Name, ſaid they: and likewiſe for their ſafety, leaſt (ſaid they) we be ſcattered abroad upon the face of the whole earth: Go to, let us build a City and a Tower; whoſe top may reach up to Heaven: here was their pride. But the only wiſe God, whoſe eye ſeeth all things, he came and took the Wiſe in their own Craftineſs, and he ſcatter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the proud in the imagination of their own hearts; all that they could do by their inventions, could not ſave them from the Wrath of the Almighty, who conſounds the Wiſdom of the Wiſe, and brings
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:168389:3"/> to nought the underſtanding of the Prudent:<note place="margin">Read <hi>Gen.</hi> 11 ch.</note> For God he came down to ſee the City and the Tower which the children of men builded, and the LORD ſaid, The People are one, and they have all one LANGUAGE, and this they beginne to doe; and nothing will be reſtrained from them which they have imagined to do; then the Lord did there confound their LANGUAGE, that they could not underſtand one ano<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hers Speech; and from thence did the Lord ſcatter them abroad upon the face of the whole earth, and ſo they left off building the City.</p>
            <p>And as men ſought out many inventions for their own ſafety and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and to make themſelves rich and great in the world, and to hide themſelves from the preſence and wrath of God; ſo likewiſe the ſaid wicked men ſought out many inventions how to deſtroy, and to affl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ct the righteous; therefore ſaid <hi>David, The wicked plotteth againſt the juſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſa. 36.4. &amp; 37.12. Pſa. 2.1, 2. Pſa. 21.11.</note> 
               <hi>and gnaſheth upon him with his teeth; he deviſeth miſchief upon his b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d; he ſetteth himſelf in a way that is not good; for the Kings of the earth ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and the rulers take counſel together, and the people imagine a va<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n thing, againſt the Lord and againſt his annointed; For</hi> ſaid Dav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d, <hi>they inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded evill againſt thee, O Lord, they imagine a miſchievous device,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Habbak. 1.4. P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o. 23. Read <hi>Pſa.</hi> the 9<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>which they are not able to perform:</hi> And Habbakkuk ſaid, <hi>the wicked doth compaſs about the righteous, the wicked are filled with miſchief, they take pleaſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e in unrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs:</hi> and ſaid <hi>Solomon, it is a ſport to a fool to do miſchi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ef:</hi> and <hi>David</hi> ſaid, <hi>O Lord, how long ſhall the wicked triumph, and all the workers of ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity boaſt themſelves?</hi> ſaid he, <hi>they break in pieces thy people, O Lord, they afflict thine heritage; they ſlay the widow and the ſtranger, and murder the fatherleſs; they frame miſchief by a Law, they gather themſelves together a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the ſoul of the righteous, and condemn the innocent blood.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cain</hi> who was the firſt born, (he ſought a wicked invention) becauſe his own works was evil, and his brothers were righteous, <hi>Cain</hi> was wrath, and his countenance fell, and he talked with his brother <hi>Abel</hi> the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, and when they were in the field, <hi>Cain</hi> roſe up againſt his brother <hi>Abel</hi> the righteous, and ſlew him; this wickedneſs was plotted, and the murder acted without any Law; but God, who heareth the cry of the innocent, and pleadeth the cauſe himſelf, of the juſt; repayed the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked for his wickedneſs; God he ſaid to <hi>Cain, what haſt thou done?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Read <hi>Gen.</hi> 4. ch. Iſa. 3.11.</note> 
               <hi>the voice of thy brothers blood cryeth unto me from the ground:</hi> now ſee what follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>wo unto the wicked, for it ſhall go ill with him;</hi> for the Lord ſaid unto <hi>Cain,</hi> Now art thou curſed from the earth; when thou titleſt the ground it ſhall not henceforth yeeld unto thee her ſtrength: a Fugitive and a Vagabond ſhall thou be in the earth: And God ſet a Mark upon <hi>Cain,</hi> leſt any finding him should kill him; for ſaid the Lord, Whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſlayeth <hi>Cain,</hi> vengeance ſhall be taken on him ſeven fold; and <hi>Cain</hi> ſaid, My puniſhment is greater then I can bear.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:168389:4"/>
            <p>And ſo the Lords of the Philiſtins, they ſought out an invention how to afflict <hi>Sampſon,</hi> and ſee here how they take counſel together, to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſh their invention; The Lords of the Philiſtines came to <hi>Delilah</hi> a woman in the valley of <hi>Sorock,</hi> whom <hi>Sampſon</hi> loved, and they ſaid unto her, <hi>Entice him, and ſee wherein his great ſtrength lyeth, and by what means we may prevail againſt him, that we may binde him to afflict him, and we will give thee every one of us eleven pieces of Silver: Now</hi> Delilah <hi>ſhe took their counſel, and accepted of the mon y, and ſought in her invention whore Sampſons ſtrength lay, and ſhe inticed Sampſon, and got out from him where his ſtrength lay, and ſhe made him ſleep upon her knees, and ſhe called for a man, and ſhe cauſed him to ſhave off the ſeven <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ocks off his head, where Sampſon ſaid his ſtrength lay; then ſhe called for the Philiſtins, ſaying, Come up this once, for he hath ſhewed me all his heart, and ſhe began to afflict him, and his ſtrength went from him; and then the Philiſtines took him and bound him with fetters of Braſs,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Read Judges, 16 chap.</note> 
               <hi>and put out his eyes, and he did grind in the priſon-houſe; then the Lords of the Philiſtines gathered them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves together, to offer a great ſacrifice unto</hi> Dagon <hi>their God, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce, and when their hearts were merry, they called for</hi> Sampſon <hi>out of the priſon-houſe to make them ſport; but God who gave</hi> Sampſon <hi>ſtrength at firſt, renewed his ſtrenth again, and took the wiſe in their own</hi> craftineſs, <hi>and made their wiſdome manifeſt to be but fooliſhneſs, and rewarded the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>circumciſed Philiſtines with judgement; and in their mirth cut them off, when they thought not on it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſo Haman, when he ſaw that <hi>Mordecai</hi> bowed not to him, nor did him reverence, according to the Kings comand, then was <hi>Haman</hi> full of wrath, and <hi>Haman</hi> was ſo proud, and ſo envious againſt the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God, that he thought ſcorn to lay hands upon <hi>Mordecai</hi> alone, therefore <hi>Haman</hi> he ſought how to deſtroy all the Jewes that were throughout the whole Kingdome, there was <hi>Hamans</hi> invention to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy all the people, for then he had no Law to do it by, for if he had had a Law, he (being ſet up above all the Princes, when he was ſo full of wrath) would have put it in execution without going to the King; Therefore <hi>Haman</hi> ſaid to the King <hi>Abaſuerus, There is a certain people ſcattered abroad, and disperſed among the people in all the Provinces of thy Kingdome, and their Laws are divers from all people; neither do they</hi> (ſaid <hi>Haman) keep the Kings Laws;</hi> therefore ſaid <hi>Haman</hi> to the King, <hi>It is not for the Kings profit to ſuffer them to live; if it pleaſe the King</hi> (ſaid <hi>Haman) let it be written that they may be deſtroyed,</hi> and ſaid <hi>Haman, I will pay ten thouſand talents of ſilver to the hands of thoſe that ſhall have the charge of the buſineſs,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Read the 3, 4, 5, 6. &amp; 7: chap. of the book of <hi>Eſther.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>to bring it into the Kings treaſuries:</hi> Here you may ſee how the Rulers and the King ſet themſelves againſt the people of God, and frame miſchief by a Law; the King took off his ring from off his hand, and gave it to <hi>Haman,</hi> and ſaid, Do with the people as
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:168389:4"/> it ſeemeth good unto thee; then was the Kings Scribes called, and all was written according to <hi>Hamans</hi> command, and the decree was made and ſealed with the Kings ſeal, and according to the writing thereof it was ſent into every Province in the kings name by the Poſts, to the Rulers of every Province, to deſtroy, to kill, and to cauſe to periſh all the Iews both young and old, little children, and women, in one day; but he that ſits in the Heavens laugh't <hi>Haman</hi> to ſcorn, and had him in deriſion daily; for <hi>Haman</hi> was taken in his own craftineſs, and his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention was diſcovered which he had ſought out, even the Gallowes which he had prepared to hang <hi>Mordecai</hi> on, and his intention to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy all the Iews according to the decree, was made manifeſt, and <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> taken and hanged upon the Gallows himſelf; the ſame meaſure that he would have meeted to others, was meeted to himſelf, up heaped.</p>
            <p>And ſo likewiſe <hi>Nebuchadnezzar,</hi> King of <hi>Babylon</hi> ſought out an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention, and made an image of Gold, threeſcore Cubits high, and ſix cubit, broad, and he ſet it up in the plain of <hi>Dura,</hi> in the Province of <hi>Babylon;</hi> then the King ſent, and gathered together the Princes, the Governors, and the Captains, the Iudges, the Counſellers, the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurers, the Sheriffs, and all the Rulers of the Provinces, to the dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Image, which the King had ſet up, and there they ſate and took counſel together, and made their invented decree, (to burn men in the invented fiery furnace) and cauſed it to be proclaimed aloud by the Harold, that whatſoever People, Nations, or Languages, did not fall down and worſhip the Golden Image, when they heard the ſound of the Cornet, Flute, Harp, Sackbut, Pſaltery, Dulcemer, and all kinds of Muſick, ſhould be the ſame hour caſt into the midſt of the fiery bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning furnace; then certain of the <hi>Caldeans</hi> accuſed the <hi>Iewes,</hi> for not falling down according to the Kings decree, to worſhip the Golden I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, which the King had ſet up; then the King in his rage and fury commanded to bring <hi>Shadrach, M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſhech,</hi> and <hi>Abedigo</hi> before him, and when they were brought before him, they told the King, they were not careful to anſwer him in that matter: For, (ſaid they) Be it known unto thee, O King, that we will not ſerve thy Gods,<note place="margin">Read the 3d. chap. of <hi>Daniel.</hi>
               </note> nor wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip the golden Image which thou haſt ſet up, behold our God whom we ſerve, is able to deliver us from the hot fiery furnace, and he will deliver us out of thy hand, O King; then was the King full of fury, and the form of his viſage was changed againſt <hi>Shadrach, Meſhech,</hi> and <hi>Obednigo,</hi> and he commanded the fiery furnace to be heated ſeventimes hotter then it was wont to be heat, and he commanded the moſt migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty men of his Army to binde <hi>Shadrach, Meſhech</hi> and <hi>Abednigo,</hi> and caſt them into the fiery furnace; therefore becauſe the Kings com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment was urgent, and the furnace exceeding hot, thoſe men <hi>Sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drach,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:168389:5"/> M ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ch,</hi> and <hi>Abednigo,</hi> were bound in their coats, their hoſen, &amp; their hats) &amp; their other garments, and were caſt into the midſt of the Fery burning Fornace. Here you may ſee how miſchief was invented, and wickedneſs acted by a Law of the King, the Princes, the Judges, the Counſellors, ond the Sheriffs, and all the Rulers of the Provinces; yea, and put in execution in the Kings rage and fury, when the form of his viſage was changed; but the moſt high and mighty God (who con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founds the wiſdom of the wiſe, and makes the Judges fools) ſuffered not the fire to have power over the bodies of his ſervants, that feared and truſted in his Name, for he ſent his Angel and delivered them; <hi>ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the hair of their heads was not ſinged, neither was their coats changed, nor th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f the fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e paſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d on <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. 26 3, 4, 14, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>5, 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>k. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>4.1.10, 11. Lu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 22.2, 3, 4, 5, 6.</note>And again the ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> Prieſts and the Scribes, with <hi>Iudas,</hi> ſought out <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n their invert on how to kill Chriſt the Son of the living God, <hi>for they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d the pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ple.</hi> Then <hi>Iudas</hi> went out from Chriſt the Light, and Satan entred into him, and he fell into the tranſgreſſion: And <hi>Iudas</hi> he went unto the ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ef Prieſts, and he communed with them and the Captains, how he migh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> betray Chriſt unto them, and they were glad, and cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanted with him for thirty p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eces of ſilver. Here you may likewiſe ſee the chief Prieſts, the Scribes, the Captains, and <hi>Iudas,</hi> how they ſate in c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>unſel together, and plotted againſt the juſt; yea, and invented miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief againſt the Lord, and againſt his anoynted, Jeſus Chriſt: From that time <hi>Iudas</hi> (in his invention) ſought opportunity how to betray Chriſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> unto them conveniently in the abſence of the multitude:<note place="margin">Joh. 18.1, 2, 3, 12, 13. Mat. 26.5, 6.</note> Then <hi>Judas</hi> having received a band of men and officers from the chief Prieſts and Phariſees, cometh with Lanthornes, and Torches, and Weapons into the Garden where Jeſus and his Diſciples were, which was over the Brook <hi>Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dron,</hi> and there the Captain, the Officers, and the Band, took Chriſt Ieſus the Son of God, and bound him, and led him away to the High Prieſt,<note place="margin">Mar. 14 53 Mar. 14.55, 56, 37. Joh. 19.7.</note> and with him were aſſembled all the chief Prieſts, the El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and Scribes: and the chief Prieſts and all the counſel (in their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventions) ſought for witneſſes againſt Ieſus, that they might put him to death; for ſaid the Iews, We have a Law, and by our Law he ought to dye; becauſe, ſaid they, he made himſelf the Son of God, &amp; they began to accuſe him before <hi>Pilate,</hi> ſaying, we have found this fellow pervert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Nation,<note place="margin">Luk. 23.1, 2. Mat. 26.59, 60, 61. Mat. 27.22.25. Luk. 23.18 23, 24.</note> and forbidding to give Tribute to <hi>Ceſar,</hi> ſaying that he himſelf is Chriſt, a King: and many bore falſe witneſs againſt him, but their witneſs agreed not together, and ſo found none: And at laſt came two falſe witneſſes, and ſaid, This fellow ſaid, I am able to deſtroy the Temple of God, and to build it in three days; and the Iews ſaid unto <hi>Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late,</hi> Away with this man, let him be crucified, and let his blood be up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us, and upon our children; and <hi>Pilate</hi> gave Sentence as they requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and they crucified him, and parted his Garments, and caſt lots
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:168389:5"/> for them. And thus you may ſee that they were the wiſe men, ſo called, and the learned Rabbies, the high Prieſts, the chief Prieſts, the Jud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, Counſellors, and Captains, that gathered themſelves together, and ſate in counſel, and upon judgement, as they called it, againſt the Lords Chriſt his annoynted;<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.19.</note> but their wiſdom is made manifeſt to be fooliſhneſs with God to after Generations: <hi>Judas</hi> hanged himſelf, and the Jews were ſcattered abroad in all Nations.</p>
            <p>And as it was then, ſo it was in after generations; that wicked men i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magined and invented miſchief againſt the ſervants of God, how to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict and deſtroy them; ſome were ſlain with the Sword, ſome had their heads cut off; ſome ſawn aſunder; ſome tortured and ſtretched upon Racks; ſome caſt into Lyons Dens, and amongſt other wilde beaſts to be devoured: Some put into boyling Caldrons; ſome ſtoned; ſome whipt; and others hanged; and ſome burned with fire; and if you wil read the Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory of the ten Perſecutions, in the firſt volume of the Book of Martyrs, ye may read of more filthy, cruel, wicked inventions that they had, and did deſtroy the people of God with, then I write of.</p>
            <p>And now to come to King <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth's dayes, you may ſee by a Statute, called <hi>the Statute Ex officio,</hi> what a Law (the learned and wiſe men, ſo called) the Biſhop, and the Clergy his brethren, the Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fragans and Aſſiſtants, had in their inventions got the King and the Houſe of Lords to make, to burn openly all thoſe people that would not in thoſe dayes worſhip the croſs, the crucifix, with other images and pictures, which in their inventions and imaginations they had ſet up to be worſhipped; or that ſhould declare by writing, preaching, or other wayes inform openly, or in ſecret, contrary to the Catholike Faith, and determination of holy Church, as they called it, and the Pope, ſhould be counted Hereticks, and openly be burned to the view of all people: and ſo eager (ſaith the Hiſtory of thoſe paſſages) were the Biſhops, and the Clergy, the Suffragans, Abbots, Priors, Deans, Arch-Deacons, Prieſts, Canons, Parſons, Vicars, Chaplains, and Clerks, to have thoſe called Hereticks to be burned, that after they had paſſed definitive Sentence upon <hi>Tho. Saultre,</hi> and delivered him over to the ſecular pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, for them to burn him, according to their invented Law, that for fear it ſhould not be done ſpeedily enough, they called upon the King, who was ready enough to ſatisfie their blood-thirſty humors, who made made a ſtrict Decree, and ſent it to the then Mayo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and Sher ffs of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> requiring them to take the ſaid <hi>Tho. Saul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> whom they had in their cuſtody, and to put him in the fire, and burn him openly and really, to the great horror of his offence; which was accordingly done; and many more after him, as the Hiſtory relates: And this cruel bloody inventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on laſted till <hi>Queen Maries</hi> dayes, and a little after; for ſee if there were not ſome of thoſe called <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> burned in queen <hi>Elizabeths</hi> dayes: And ſo you may ſee here, how man whom God created upright,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 7.26.</note> ſought
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:168389:6"/> out many wicked inventions, and plotted againſt the juſt, and ſet them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and took counſel together againſt the Lord, and againſt his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noynted, and imagined mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>chief both by a Law, and without a Law, ſaying, Let us break their bonds aſunder, &amp; caſt away their cords from off us;<note place="margin">Pſa. 2.3.</note> and as the heathen did rage then, ſo they do now; and as the people imagined vain things then, ſo they do now in theſe dayes imagine vain things, and ſeek out new inventions, whereby to afflict the ſervants of the living God.</p>
            <p>So here followeth a new Invention, ſought out by mans imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, and in mans will is acted as he ſits in Judgement, ſo called; for which he hath neither Law from God or man, to bear him out in paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing his Sentence, as ſome of thoſe who are counted grave, wiſe Judges of this Land have done upon ſome of thoſe people called quakers, and ſetting a Fine of twenty Marks a piece upon them, and ſent them to pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to lye there till payment of the ſame; and for their ſo doing, I ſay they have neither Law from God, nor no Law of this Nation to bear them out; but what is done in this caſe, is done without any law upon the innocent, who have tranſgreſſed no law by ſtanding with their hats on their heads in open Court before the Juſtices of Aſſiſes, for the which they are fined twenty Marks a piece, and ſent to priſon till payment of the ſame; for where there is no law, there is no tran<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>greſſion; therefore the parties are innocent in this thing, by keeping their hats on their heads, and not putting them off to ſtand bare-headed before them in the Court: and where there is no law to tranſgreſs, there ought no ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence to paſs upon any man, for puniſhment to be inflicted, either by death, or loſs of limb, bani<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hment, or impriſonment, nor no Fine ſet to to the confiſcation of Goods, unleſs there were a law given, with a pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalty thereunto, to be inflicted upon the tranſgreſſors thereof. And therefore I ſay, Whatſoever Judge or Juſtice that paſſeth Judgement upon any man, or men, for which he hath no law, acts in his own will, and by his own invention, contrary to the rule of the law, which is ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, juſt, pure and good, given forth by the pure law giver, Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, and is written in their heart, according to the <hi>Covenant</hi> of God, who ſaith <hi>he hath ſhewed thee, O man, what is good; and what the Lord doth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire of thee, but to do juſtly, and to love mercy, and to walk humbly with thy God? who ſtandeth in the Congregation of the mighty, and judgeth among the Iudges,</hi> ſaying, <hi>How long will ye judge unjuſtly, and accept the perſons of the wicked?</hi> ſaith the Lord; <hi>defend the poor and fatherleſs, do juſtice to the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted and needy:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſa. 82.</note> You Judges, the Lord God ſaith, You muſt deliver the POORE and NEEDY, and rid them out of the hands of the wicked, and ſee that ye reſpect no mans perſon in judgement: for with the Lord there is no reſpect of perſons, nor taking of gifts: Therefore you are not to judge for man, but for the Lord; and upon the Tranſgreſſors of the Law are you to inflict puniſhment, and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:168389:6"/> not upon the juſt, as ſome of you have done here in <hi>England,</hi> upon ſome of thoſe people called <hi>quakers,</hi> for not putting off their hats, and not ſtanding bareheaded before you in your Court, and for no other thing, whom ye ought to have ſet at liberty, and ſo have rid them out of the hands of the wicked; for I tell, that if they had put off their hats, and ſtood bare-headed before you, reſpecting your perſons, then they had tranſgreſſed the law, as ſaith the Scripture; for <hi>James,</hi> a witneſs of Chriſt,<note place="margin">James 2.9</note> and a Miniſter of the Word, ſaid, <hi>but if ye have respect to perſons, ye com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit ſin, and are convinced of the Law as Tranſgreſſors; for whoſoever ſhall offend in one point, he is guilty of all; and he that reſpecteth mens perſons, hath not the faith of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> for Chriſt Jeſus ſaid, <hi>How can ye be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve that receive honour one of another, and ſeek not the honour that cometh from God only?</hi> Chriſt Jeſus leaving us an example,<note place="margin">Joh. 5.44. 1 Pet. 2.21. Mat. 22.16 Mark 12.14. Luke 20.21. 1 Joh. 3.4, 6, 8, 9, 10.</note> that we ſhould fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low his ſteps, who reſpected no mans perſon: And God ſaith, <hi>Ye ſhall do no unrighteouſneſs in judgement; thou ſhalt not reſpect the perſon of the poore, nor honour the perſon of the mighty; he that respecteth mens perſons commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth ſin by tranſgreſſing the Law; for every ſin is the tranſgreſſion of the Law: and he that committeth ſin is not of God, but of the devil,</hi> as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aith the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; <hi>but every knee ſhall bow to the Name of Ieſus, and every tongue ſhall confeſs him to be Lord and King:</hi> and the Lord God alone is to be wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped; and the people of his Paſture, and the ſheep of his hand, they worſhip him in ſpirit and in truth, and come and bow, and kneel down before the Lord their Maker, and not to man. <hi>Mordecai</hi> would not bow to <hi>Haman,</hi> nor do him reverence according to the Kings command, which was contrary to Gods command. <hi>Shadrach, M ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ch,</hi> and <hi>Abed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nigo</hi> would not bow down to the golden Image that the King had ſet up, nor worſhip his Gods, according to the Kings command, which was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to Gods command.</p>
            <p>ANd yet I ſay, that the great God of heaven and earth commands <hi>every ſoul to be ſubject to the higher powers for conſcience ſake,</hi> which are ordained of God; and likewiſe <hi>to ſubmit to every O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nance of man for the Lords ſake;</hi> and to honour all men, and to honour the K<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ow to honour all men is not to riſe up and bow down to them, as the faſhion of this world is, and to ſtand bare-headed before men, as it is the practiſe of the world ſo to do one to another, upon every occaſion that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hey have to do with thoſe that are greater in the worlds eſtimation in riches, and have higher places and titles of honour in the world then them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and ſo have their perſons in admiration for their advantage ſake: Nay, this is not honouring all men, nor no man, but meer flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery; for all this a man may do, and yet at the very ſame time hate the man in his heart, and ſeek his Neighbours hurt; therefore ſaid <hi>Solomon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 20.19. &amp; 26.28. &amp; 29.5.</note> Meddle not with him that hath flattering lips, for a man that flattereth his Neighbour ſpreadeth a Net for his feet; and ſayes he, A flattering
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:168389:7"/> mouth worketh ruin: therefore ſaid, <hi>Elihu,</hi> Let me not I pray you ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept any mans perſon,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob</hi> 22.21, <hi>Iob</hi> 17.5.</note> neither let me give flattering titles unto man; for I know, ſaid he, to give flattering titles, in ſo doing my Maker would ſoon take me away: and <hi>Iob</hi> ſaid, He that ſpeaketh flattery to his friends, even the eyes of his children ſhall fail: and ſuch flattery was u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by <hi>Saul</hi> to <hi>David;</hi> and likewiſe by <hi>Sauls</hi> ſervants to <hi>David;</hi> to be the Kings Son in-law, and to have his eldeſt Daughter to his wife, to be a ſnate to him; as you may read 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> chap. 18. toward the latter end: And ſo <hi>Iudas</hi> came to Chriſt, and ſaid, <hi>Hail Maſter,</hi> and kiſſed him; and for money the ſame time betrayed him to the <hi>Iews.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.47, 48, 49.</note> And ſo a Thief, a Rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, or Murderer, he will put off his hat and ſtand b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> headed before a Magiſtrate, Judge or Juſtice, who could finde in his heart at the ſame time, if he had but the Magiſtrate, Judge or Juſtice upon <hi>Black-Heath,</hi> or <hi>Salisbury-Plain,</hi> to rob and take all he hath from him, and his life too.</p>
            <p>And is this honour? nay: To honour all men conſiſts in doing good to all men, as we would be done unto our ſelves by others; and in lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving all men, even our neigbour as our ſelves; and in doing good to all men, and ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>king every mans good; for ſaid Chriſt, <hi>if ye love them that love <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ou,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.46.</note> 
               <hi>what reward have you? do not even the publicanes the ſame?</hi> Did the Publicanes honour all men? nay, but their friends only; and what reward had they? <hi>the world loves its own;</hi> therefore they honour not all men; but they that honour all men, love continually, pray for their enemies, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o good <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o them that hate them, and overcom evil with good; when they ſee their enemies hungry, they give them meat; when they ſee them thirſty, they give them drink; and naked, they clothe them: and they that honour all men, are no backbiters, nor ſlanderers, nor falſe accuſers, nor <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>peak evil of any man; for love thinketh no evil, but ſeeketh all mens good, and not their own; nor are they eaſily provoked, nor b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>have themſelves unſeemly, but are gentle, enduring all things, and rejoyc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng in the truth.</p>
            <p>NEither doth the honour which is to be given unto the Magiſtrate, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hether it be to a King, as ſupreme; or to a Lord Protector, as chief; or to any Ruler, Governor, Judge, or Juſtice, or other Officer, either alone or before them in open Court of Judicature, conſiſt in ſtanding up, and bowing down the body to them, nor in putting the hat off, and ſtanding bareheaded before them; but the honour which is to be given to the Magiſtrate, conſiſts in love, obedience and fear: for he that doth evil is to be afraid, ſeeing that the Ruler is ſet up of God to be a terror to evil doers; therefore he that ruleth muſt be juſt, ruling in the fear of God, and not to bear his ſword in vain, but to lay it upon the evil-doers, who are to fear (the Ruler) becauſe they have done the evil, and he is ſet up of the Lord to be a terror to them: but he that doth
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:168389:7"/> no evil, needs not to fear: For doing that wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ch is good, he is to have praiſe of the ſame; for the Ruler is ſet up of God likewiſe for the praiſe of them that do well: Therefore he that is in the well-doing, needs not fear the Rulers ſword; for Perfect love caſts out fear, and The righteous is bold as a lyon: So likewiſe the honour which is to be given to the Magiſtrate, conſiſts in love: he that is in the well-doing, loves the Magiſtrate, becauſe <hi>he is ſet up of God to be a terror to the evil doers,</hi> and <hi>a protection to them that do well:</hi> and love to the Magiſtrate conſiſts in ſeeking his good always, and in giving to him his due that God requires to give unto him: and thoſe that give to the Magiſtrate his due, ſpeak not evil of the Ruler of the People, nor re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vile the Judges, no nor curſe the Magiſtrate or Ruler in their thoughts, which is contrary to Gods Command: But for the Lords ſake he loves the Magiſtrate, and dares not riſe up in his own will againſt him for conſcience ſake, and for that cauſe pays tribute, and ſo likewiſe is ſubject to what is required by the Magiſtrate that comes from God: and for conſcience ſake that which comes from God by the Magiſtrate, is not gain-ſaid, but ſubmitted to by them that honour the Magiſtrate for the Lords ſake: And herein the People of <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſhewed their will<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingneſs to obey that of God, that came from God to them by <hi>Moſes</hi> their Ruler: For, ſaid they to <hi>Moſes,</hi> Go thou neer and heare all that the Lord our Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſhall ſay,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ut.</hi> 5.27, 28.</note> and ſpeak thou unto us all that the Lord our God ſhall ſpeak unto thee, and we will hear it, and do it: and the Lord ſaid, This People have ſaid well in all that they have ſpoken. So likewiſe the chief of the Fathers, and the Princes of the Tribes of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and the Captains over thouſands and hundreds; with the Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers over <hi>David</hi> the kings work joyned with <hi>David,</hi> and offered wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly to the Lord, and gave for the ſervice of the houſe of God, gold, ſilver, iron, and pretious ſtones:<note place="margin">1 <hi>Chro.</hi> 29.</note> and with a perfect heart they offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red willingly to the Lord, and rejoyced: and <hi>David</hi> the king rejoyced alſo with great joy, becauſe the thing was of the Lord: which was ſo willingly done by them, according to the Command of the Lord God who ſaith, <hi>Hea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> O</hi> Iſrael, <hi>VVhat doth the Lord require of thee, but to fear the Lord thy God, and to walk in all his ways, and to love him, and to ſerve the Lord thy God with all thy heart and with all thy ſoul, and to keep the Commandments of the Lord and his Statutes, which ſaith the Lord, I command thee this day for thy good?</hi> Now whatſoever comes from any Ruler or Magiſtrate contrary to the Lord God and his Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, the ſervants of the Lord obey not, but rather chooſe to ſuffer afflictions by ſubmitting to every Ordinance of man for the Lords ſake, then to obey the Magiſtrates Command which is contrary to Gods Command. For if the Magiſtrate make an Ordinance to take a man that fears the Lord God, and to bring him before him, the man that fears the Lord for the Lords ſake who commands him, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:168389:8"/> unto the Ordinance of man: he patiently and willingly goes whither the Officer will have him: and if the Magiſtrate make an Ordinance to ſend him to priſon, he goes willingly, not reſiſting a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it, for the Lords ſake, if it be to ſuffer ſtripes by vertue of that Ordinance; they bear it patiently, not ſtriving nor crying out; if it be to ſuffer death by vertue of the Magiſtrates Ordinance. They that love the Lord, are not only willing to ſuffer, but ready alſo to dye for the ſake of Jeſus, and for obeying the Commandments of the Lord God. And herein did <hi>Shadrach, Meſhach</hi> and <hi>Ab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dnego</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe to obey the kings command, which was to worſhip his gods, and to bow to the Image which he had ſett up, which to do was contrary to Gods Command: ſo for the Lords ſake they ſubmitted patiently to the kings Ordinance, which was to be caſt into the fiery burning fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nace for diſobeying the Kings Command: And ſo did <hi>Daniel</hi> refuſe to obey the Kings Command, which was that no man ſhould ask any Petition of any god or man for thirty days ſave only of the King, which was contrary to the Command of God <hi>[Pray continually]</hi> for which Command of obeying God, and refuſing to obey the Kings, <hi>Daniel</hi> ſubmitted to the Kings Ordinance, which was to be caſt into the ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons den: And ſo <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaid that they could not forbear to ſpeak the things which they had ſeen and heard concerning Jeſus, which was according to Chriſts Command, notwithſtanding that the High-prieſt, the Rulers, the Elders and the Scribes commanded them to preach no more in the name of Jeſus: And if the Magiſtrate make an Ordinance to take away the goods of thoſe that fear God, and obey his Commandments, they for the Lords ſake ſubmit to the Ordinance of man, and ſuffer the ſpoyling of their goods willingly and patiently, rather then to tranſgreſs the Law which is holy, pure and good, given forth by the pure Lawgiver Chriſt Jeſus; And they revile not again; being curſed they bleſs: and although they ſuffer wrongfully, yet they threaten not, but commit themſelves and their cauſe to God which judgeth righteouſly: And herein do they that fear the Lord follow Chriſt, who ſuffered for us, leaving us an Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, that we ſhould follow his ſteps, who commands to fear God, and to honour all men, and to honour the King, and to ſubmitt to every Ordinance of man for the Lords ſake, whether it be to the King as ſupreme, or unto other Governors as unto thoſe that are ſent for the puniſhment of Evil-doers, and for the praiſe of them that do well. And herein is Submiſſion and Subjection declared; which is accordingly done by the Servants of the moſt high God, not for wrath, but for conſcience ſake towards God.</p>
            <p>And again I ſay it is no ſin to ſtand with my hat on before the higher Powers, becauſe <hi>VVhere there is no Law, there is no tranſgreſſion;</hi> For every day I goe about my Occaſions at home and abroad, and ſtand
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:168389:8"/> or ſit with my hat on my head before the great God of I heaven and earth my Maker in his ſight and preſence, out of which I cannot goe, who is the higheſt of all Powers: and for ſo doing my conſcience doth not accuſe me for ſin. For I know that if it were a ſin, that of God in my conſcience would condemn me for ſo doing: and if my conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence did condemn me, God is greater who would condemn me alſo: And ſeeing it is no ſin for me to walk, ſit or ſtand with my hat on my head before the great God of heaven and earth, who is the higheſt of Powers, by whom Kings raign; then it is no ſin for me to ſtand with my hat on my head before the leſſer Powers: And if it be no ſin for me to ſtand with my hat on my head before the great God of heaven and earth that lives for ever; then it is no ſin for me to ſtand with my hat on my head before them that are called Gods, who ſhall dye like men. And again, if it be no ſin for me to ſtand with my hat on my head before the King of Kings, and Lord of Lords (which ſitteth amongſt them and the Judges) and hath power to pull down one, and ſet up another; then it is no ſin for me to ſtand with my hat on my head before a King, Lord, Judge, Juſtice or any other Magiſtrate, who have no Law from him by whom they rule to command me to take my hat off, and ſtand bare-headed before them in reſpect to their perſons.</p>
            <p>And again, the putting off the hat, and the ſtanding bare-headed before the Ruler, Judge or Juſtice, or other Magiſtrate, ſingly and alone or before them in the Courts of Judicature, as the multitude of the world doth, is but eye-ſervice done to pleaſe the Magiſtrate, while his eye is on them, and they in his ſight; But thoſe that fear the Lord, they deny all eye-ſervice, For whatſoever they do they do it in ſingleneſs of heart as unto the Lord, and not unto man, or to pleaſe man in reſpect to their perſons, contrary to the Command of God. For I tell you both Judges and Juſtices, that thoſe People that put their hats off and ſtand bare-headed before you while they are in your ſight, in reſpect to your perſons which you call honour, even they will and do, when they are out of your ſight tranſgreſs all laws (with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any fear at all of you, And what honour is this?) by ſwearing, lying, curſing, drunkenneſs, adultery, fornication, robbing, ſtealing, fighting, quarrelling, murder and bloodſhed, plotting how to ſett the wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>le Nation together by the cars, that thereby they might rule themſelves over all, as daily Experience makes manifeſt, and ye your ſelves be witneſſes againſt them, who are brought before you for ſuch tranſgreſſions, whom ye ought to puniſh for their evil deeds, and mind to do juſtice and judgement in the fear of the Lord, and take no notice of their hats (but of their evil deeds) for their hats do no evil, nor tranſgreſs no law, but do good by keeping of the head warm, and covering of it from the heat, cold and wet; and for this
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:168389:9"/> end let them keep on their hats as they do their other garments, and ſee that they honor God by leaving off their ſins, and then there will be honour to the Magiſtrate indeed given for conſcience-ſake, and the Land will be cleanſed of evil doers: Now the rayment is for the body, and given of God to Man to put on; For, (ſaid <hi>Iacob</hi>) if the Lord will give me bread to eat, and rayment to put on: And <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaid, The Lord loveth the Stranger in giving him rayment; now the hat is one part of the rayment, which God hath given to man to cover his nakedneſs, for which it is to be put and kept on the body, which is for the Lord; ſo likewiſe the rayment is to keep the body from the cold, and the wet, and alſo from the parching heat of the Sun: Now ſeeing that God hath given unto all man-kind rayment for theſe cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes to put on, to cover the body with, then why ſhould one man com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand another to take it off, and to uncover himſelf, or any part of his body, for which his rayment is given to him to be a covering thereof? Now all you who take mens hats from off their heads, and make them to ſtand bare-headed at your pleaſure, you act contrary to God and his command, who ſaith, <hi>Do violence to no man.</hi> God he clothes man, and will you unclothe him, or any part of him? God he loves the Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger in giving of him rayment: and will you make a profeſſion of God and Chriſt, and when a Stranger comes before you, will you cauſe his hat which is pair of his rayment, to be pulled off from his head, and to ſtand bare-headed to take cold, or to be over-heat with the heat of the Sun, or to be wet with the rain or ſnow; and will you have him to ſuffer theſe things, or any of them, by ſtanding bare-headed in reſpect to your perſons? if ye wil, leave off making a profeſſion of God, for God is not mocked; But ſome of you (it is like) will ſay, that he may put on a cap, or two caps on his head, Is not that all one? For, is not the cap, or caps, made to cover the head, and to keep it warm, as well as the hats? And why are you more offended with a man that ſtands before you with a hat on his head, then you are with another that ſtands before you with a cap, or two caps upon his head, ſeeing that there is no law for one to tranſgreſs more then the other? Do not you ſhew your ſelves to be partial herein? And again, every man it is like is not provided with a cap ready to put on his head, and ſome are poor, and have not money to buy a cap or two with; and why ſhould the poor man be compelled to ſtand bare-headed to get cold more then the rich? Or, again, Why ſhould one that fears God, and cannot for conſcience towards God put off his hat, and ſtand bare-headed before you in reſpect to your perſons, be compelled to ſtand bare-headed when it is taken off from him, as the Swearer, Drunkard, Thief, Rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and Murderer can do, (who tranſgreſs the Law) onely to pleaſe you, and do it not out of any fear or Obedience <hi>to God.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:168389:9"/>
            <p>And again ſome have ſaid, That to put off the hat, and to ſtand bare-headed before the Magiſtrate is the cuſtome of this Nation; and therefore it is to be kept and obſerved before the Magiſtrate.</p>
            <p>But, God he commands the contrary, as the Scripture with me doth witneſs: For, ſaith the Lord, <hi>Thou ſhalt not follow a multitude to do evil: neither ſhalt thou ſpeak in a cauſe to decline after many to wreſt judgment; neither ſhalt thou do after the works of the Canaanites, the Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vites, the Perizites, the Hittites and the Iebuſites.</hi> And Solomon ſaid, <hi>The way of the wicked is an abomination unto the Lord:</hi> And, <hi>If ſinners entice thee, conſent thou not to them.</hi> Therefore thoſe that are the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of the Lord God are not to to do after the manner of the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, nor to follow a multitude to do evil, nor to faſhion thmſelves according to the World, and as they did in the time of their ignorance according to their former Luſts, when they walked in a vain converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion received by tradition from their Fathers: By following of which Traditions, they tranſgreſſed the Commandments of God,<note place="margin">Mat. 15.3.</note> but being called to holineſs of converſation, in obedience to God they are to obſerve no ſuch Traditions.</p>
            <p>But ſome have ſaid that the Cuſtome of the Nation is law; and like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe that the Law maintains the Nations Cuſtomes.</p>
            <p>If the putting off the hat, and ſtanding bare-headed before the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate, either alone or in open Court, be a Cuſtome, and that the Law of the Land maintains it for a Cuſtome, then let any of the Judges or Counſellors of the Land make known that Law, that maintain it for a Cuſtome: or let them ſhew one Preſident for it, or whoſe Caſe it was in law that was ſo fined, and ſent to priſon till pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the ſaid Fine of twenty Marks; or whatever parties goods were ever diſtrained of for not paying the ſaid Fine; or whether ever any Fine was brought into the Exchequer for ſuch a thing; and in what King or Queens Reigns it was in, ſince <hi>VVilliam</hi> the Conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors time, that any man or men were fined twenty Marks a piece, and ſent to priſon till payment of the ſame, by any Judge of juſtice of the Engliſh Nation: or let them ſhew me any Example from any one Judge, Ruler or King, that judged, or ruled over Iſrael, or from any of the Heathen Kings that the Scripture ſpeaks of.</p>
            <p>For <hi>Moſes,</hi> he was a Ruler and a Judg over Iſrael, and the Scripture doth not anywhere teſtify that he ſet a Fine upon any man for not putting off his hat, and ſtanding bare-headed before him; nor ſent any <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>an to priſon for any ſuch thing; neither did he give any charge or Command to the Judges that judged the People at all ſeaſons, ſo to do. For ſaid Moſes, <hi>I charged your Iudges at that time, ſaying,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 18.25, 26.</note> 
               <hi>Hear the Cauſes between your Brethrens and judge righteouſly between every man and his brother, and the ſtranger that is with him: ye ſhall not r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>spect perſons in judgment, but you ſhall hear the ſmall as well as the great; you
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:168389:10"/> ſhall not be afraid of the face of man,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 1.16, 17.</note> 
               <hi>for the judgment is Gods. And the Cauſe that is too hard for you, bring it before me, and I will hear it,</hi> and in this charge there is no mention made of hats to be put off by the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, nor ſtanding bare-headed before them, neither do I find that <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhua</hi> who was a Ruler over Iſrael after <hi>Moſes,</hi> that he fined any man, and ſent him to priſon for not putting off his Hat, and not ſtanding bare headed before him; neither did he give any charge to the heads of the people, the Rulers, Judges, and Officers ſo to do; for <hi>Ioſhua</hi> called them together, and ſaid to them, I am old and ſtricken in age, be ye therefore very couragious to keep, and to do all that is written in the book of the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Joſh. 23.2.6, 11, ver.</note> that ye turn not aſide there-from, to the right hand, or to the left; take good heed therefore unto your ſelves, that you love the Lord your God. Did <hi>Gideon, Jeptha, Deborah, Sampſon, Eli, Samuel,</hi> or any other of the Judges that judged Iſrael, command the people to put off their hats, and to ſtand bare-headed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them? or fine and ſend any to priſon, to lie there till payment of the ſaid fine, for not putting their hats off, and ſtanding not bare-headed before them? Or did any of the Kings of Iſrael and Judah that feared the Lord, as <hi>David, Solomon, Jehoſaphat, Joſiah,</hi> or <hi>Hezeki<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah,</hi> or others that feared the Lord, command any man to put off his hat, and to ſtand bare-headed before them? Or if they did not, did a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny one of them fine any man, and ſend him to priſon to lie there till payment of the ſaid fine? (as ſome of the Judges of this Nation have done to ſome of thoſe people called <hi>quakers:</hi>) Or, did any of thoſe Kings give any charge to the Judges ſo to do to the people that did not put off their hats, and ſtand bare-headed before them, yea or nay? For I finde that <hi>Jehoſaphat</hi> ſet Judges in the Land, throughout all the fenced Cities of <hi>Judah,</hi> City by City, and he ſaid to the Judges, Take heed what ye do;<note place="margin">2 Chro. 19.5, 6, 7.</note> for ye judg not for man, but for the Lord, who is with you in judgment: Wherefore, ſaid he, now let the fear of the Lord be upon you, take heed, and do it; for there is no iniquity with the Lord our God, nor reſpect of perſons, nor taking of gifts; and in this charge to all the Judges by <hi>Jehoſaphat,</hi> here was no mention made of hats, or did any of the idolatrous Kings ot Iſrael and Judah, as <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoboam, Jeroboam, Zimri, Ahab, Zedekiah,</hi> or others of thoſe Kings, command the people to put off their hats, and to ſtand bare-headed before them, or did they ſet fines upon any of the people that did not put off their hats, and ſtand bare headed before them, or ſend them to priſon till payment of the ſame, yea or nay? Or did any of the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then Kings which the Scripture ſpeaks of, as <hi>Pharoah</hi> King of <hi>Egypt,</hi> or <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> King of <hi>Babylon,</hi> or <hi>Caeſar, Herod,</hi> or others, fine any man, and lend him to priſon to lie there till payment of the ſaid fine, for not putting off their hats, and ſtanding not bare-headed before them, yea or nay?</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:168389:10"/>
            <p>You Judges of <hi>England,</hi> who have done thus, ſee if you have any precedent for what you have done, or any example in all the Scriptures; and if you have not, then to that of God in every one of your conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences that bears me witneſs, that you have exceeded all the Kings, Rulers and Judges, that ever have gone before you, in this invention that ye have ſought out now of late; And what do you make a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of God, and of Chriſt, and ſeek out inventions? And are not you aſhamed that you are diſcovered by the light, to be in the inventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and to exceed therein beyond the very Heathen that have gone before you, which are ſpoken of in the Scripture? I am ſure you have no example from <hi>Oliver,</hi> Protector, for this; for he never ſet any fine upon any man, no nor ſent any man to priſon, for ſtanding with his hat on his head before him, neither did I ever hear that he was offended with any man, or men, for their ſo doing; and I am ſure that he and his Council have not made any Law for you to act ſo by; if they had, it would have been publiſhed as well as others have been: And ſeeing you have no example from <hi>Oliver</hi> Protector, nor any Law from him and his Council for your ſo doing; then I appeal to all un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding men, whether you do not diſgrace his Government, and diſhonor him the chief Ruler of the Common-wealth, by doing ſuch things in the Corners of the Land in his name, for which you have neither Law, nor Example from him for your ſo doing, whom ye ought to honor, as well as others. And now to you the Judges, who have ſet fines upon men, and ſent them to priſon to lie there till payment of the ſame, for nothing but becauſe they could not for conſcience ſake towards God, and in reſpect to your perſons, put off their hats, and ſtand bare-headed before you; I ſay, Stand ſtill a little while, and commune with your own hearts, and ſee whether you have kept the Law of God, and judged for the Lord in this thing: or, whether you have not gone beyond the rule that God hath ſhewed you; that is, <hi>He hath ſhewed thee, O Man, what is good, and what the Lord doth requ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re of thee; but to do juſtly, and to love mercy, and to walk humbly with thy God:</hi> Have you done thus yea or nay? Or,<note place="margin">Judges Oath, 18 <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. Stat. 3.</note> ſee if ye have done ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to your own Law and Oath; that is, <hi>That ye ſhall do even Law and execution of right to all Subjects rich and poor, without having <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>egard to any perſon, and in caſe any Letters come to you contrary to the Law, that yee do nothing by ſuch Letters, and go forth and do the Law; and by the Law no man of what eſtate or condition that he be,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Anno</hi> 28 <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. ch. 3.</note> 
               <hi>ſhall be put from his Land or Tenement, or taken and impriſoned, or diſ-inherited, or put death, without being brought into anſwer by due proceſs of Law;</hi> now ſee if yee have gone according to your own rule, and kept within your own bounds, and if yee have not kept within your own rule which is but mans Law, neither have you any Law from God to act ſo by; then conſider, How do you think to execuſe your ſelves, when the Lord
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:168389:11"/> God ſhall call you to an account, and ſay, <hi>VVho hath required this at your hands?</hi> What anſwer will you make him? What have you to ſhew, whereby to juſtifie your ſelves? How do you think to ſtand be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord in judgement, that have done ſuch things againſt his ſervants, who ſaith, <hi>Touch not mine annoynted, and do my Prophets no harm;</hi> and you that have touched them, have touched the apple of his eye, for they are his Jewels, and Chriſt ſayes, What ye have done unto them, he takes as done unto himſelfe: Therefore I tell you it were better for you, that you had never been born, or that a milſtone were hanged about your necks, and you caſt into the Sea, then to offend the leaſt of theſe little ones, except you ſpeedily repent.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Be wiſe therefore now, O yee Kings, be inſtructed ye Iudges of the earth; ſerve the Lord with fear, ſerve him in love, and in ſingleneſs of heart; Kiſs the Sun, leſt he be angry, and ye periſh from the way when his wrath is kindled; while you have time prize it, and humble your ſelves before the Lord, and ſubmit your ſelves under the mighty power of God; For now is the day of your viſitation, and to day if ye will hear his voyce, harden not your hearts, but fear the Lord God, which is the beginning of wiſdom, which will guide you to do true judgement, and the fear of the Lord is to depart from iniquity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is written to be printed, that every Ruler, Judge, and Juſtice, or other Officer in this Nation may each have one, and that thoſe friends into whoſe hands this book ſhall come, may ſend them to thoſe Rulers, Judges, or Juſtices that they know, that all they who have not yet acted ſuch things as is herein contained, may (if they fear the Lord, and rule, and judge for him) be prevented, and that the other may be left without excuſe, that are without his fear, acting in their own wills, by their own inventions, againſt the Lord, and againſt his annoynted.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Henry Clark.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>The End.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
